<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="chapter-intro" xreflabel="Chapter 1">
<?dbhtml dir="chapter01"?>
	<title>Introduction</title>
<?dbhtml filename="chapter01.html"?>
	<section id="ch-intro-purpose">
		<title>Purpose</title>
		<para>This document provides a functional specification for the software
		      tool <quote>alfs</quote>
		</para>
	</section>

	<section id="ch-intro-audience">
		<title>Intended Audience</title>
		<para>This document is targeted toward users and developers of the
		      <quote>alfs</quote> tool.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section id="ch-intro-scope">
		<title>Scope</title>
		<para>This document covers the high level descriptions of all the
		      functionality that the <quote>alfs</quote> tool will provide.  The
		      scope of this document will be limited to describing what features
		      will be made available, and therefore will not go into detail on
		      any specific programming languages or development tools.
	  </para>
	</section>

	<section id="ch-intro-name">
		<title>Product Name</title>
		<para>The tool is called <quote>alfs</quote>.  It is important it be
		      written entirely in lowercase to differentiate it from the project
			  name it is a part of (ALFS).
		</para>
		<para>The project is the tool and the tool is the project, so the name
		      should fit inside this idea and is why the name
		      <quote>alfs</quote> was chosen.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section id="ch-intro-defs">
		<title>Definitions, Acronymns, and Abbreviations</title>
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>ALFS</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Automated Linux From Scratch  an open architecture of
					      automating the build of an LFS system using an XML
					      based profile.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term>XML</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Extensible Markup Language (XML) is a simple, very
					      flexible text format that is playing an increasingly
					      important role in the exchange of a wide variety of
					      data on the Web and elsewhere. [1]
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Client/Server</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>A model of computing architecture where a component
					      application runs on one computer and another runs on a
					      remote server computer.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
	</section>
	<section id="ch-intro-refs">
		<title>References</title>
		<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<ulink url="http://w3.org/XML/"/>
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>
	</section>
	<section id="ch-intro-overview">
		<title>Overview</title>
		<para><quote>alfs</quote> is a tool that is used to simplify and
		      automate the tasks that installing and managing software packages
		      on a Linux system require. Its primary goal is to automate the LFS
		      build procedure. Using a standard documented protocol,
		      <quote>alfs</quote> will accept instructions, validate them, and
		      carry out the specific tasks that correspond to these higher-level
		      orders.  <quote>alfs</quote> will then report back on the outcomes
		      of its actions.
		</para>
	</section>
</chapter>
