<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="chapter-intro" xreflabel="Chapter 1">
<?dbhtml dir="chapter01"?>
<title>Introduction</title>
<?dbhtml filename="chapter01.html"?>

<section id="ch-intro-purpose">
<title>Purpose</title>
<para>This document aims to provide a concrete specification describing the
software tool alfs. Readers of this document should have a basic understanding
of XML, networks, and the client/server model.</para>
</section>

<section id="ch-intro-scope">
<title>Scope</title>
<para>This document will cover all the fundamental concepts that together will
form the alfs tool. The scope of this document will be limited to the ideas that
surround this tool and will not go into detail on any specific programming
languages or development tools.</para>
</section>

<section id="ch-intro-name">
<title>Product Name</title>
<para>After some healthy debate and work on the mailing lists, the tool will be
named simply &quot;alfs&quot;.  We write it in all lowercase to differentiate it
somewhat from the project name it is named after (ALFS).  The project is the
tool and the tool is the project, so the name should fit inside this idea and is
why we have selected this name.</para>
</section>

<section id="ch-intro-defs">
<title>Definitions, Acronymns, and Abbreviations</title>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>ALFS</term>
    <listitem><para>Automated Linux From Scratch &ndash; an open architecture of
      automating the build of an LFS system using an XML based profile.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry>
    <term>XML</term>
    <listitem><para>Extensible Markup Language (XML) is a simple, very flexible
     text format that is playing an increasingly important role in the exchange
     of a wide variety of data on the Web and elsewhere. [1]</para></listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry>
    <term>Client/Server</term>
    <listitem><para>A model of computing architecture where a component
      application runs on one computer and another runs on a remote server
      computer.</para></listitem>
  </varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>

<section id="ch-intro-refs">
<title>References</title>
<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
  <listitem><para><ulink url="http://w3.org/XML/"/></para></listitem>
</orderedlist>
</section>

<section id="ch-intro-overview">
<title>Overview</title>
<para>alfs is a tool that is used to simplify and automate the tasks that
installing and managing software packages on a Linux system require. Its primary
goal is to automate the LFS build procedure. Using a standard documented
protocol, alfs will accept instructions, validate them, and carry out the
specific tasks that correspond to these higher-level orders. alfs will then
report back on the outcomes of its actions.</para>
</section>
</chapter>
