<sect1 id="hacker-distro-tarballs" xreflabel="Distribution Tarballs">
<?dbhtml filename="distro_tarballs.html" dir="hacker"?>
<title>Distribution Tarballs</title>

<para>When you are ready to produce a tarball for distribution, there are a
few steps to follow:</para>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Check out a clean copy of the nALFS repository. Using an
existing copy, especially one that has been configured and used as a build
tree, can potentially cause errors in the <command>make dist</command> process.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Edit <filename>bootstrap.configure</filename>, and modify
the line starting with AC_INIT to reflect the version number that you want
the distribution to be given (replace &quot;CVS&quot; with your desired
version number). Do not commit this change to the CVS repository, as the
CVS version should always report its version number as
&quot;CVS&quot;.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Run <command>sh ./bootstrap -d CVS -g CVS -p 5.0</command>.
This command will create the configure script and Makefile (as is normally
done with a CVS checkout), but will also download, extract and rename the
documentation files that will be included in the tarball. These files
include the DTD (the current CVS version), the syntax document describing
the DTD, the user's guide and the hacker's guide. The latter three
documents are currently downloaded from James Robertson's home directory on
the LFS server, but see the URL_BASE variable in the bootstrap script to
change the download source. In addition, the LFS-5.0 profile will be
downloaded so it can be included in the tarball.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Run <command>./configure</command> specifying any
parameters your system needs to complete the configuration
process.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Run <command>make dist</command>. This will produce both a
<filename>.tar.gz</filename> and a <filename>.tar.bz2</filename> file in
the current directory containing everything that should be needed to build
&book-product; on an end-user's system. Note that this tarball will be
created using the <filename>autoconf</filename>,
<filename>automake</filename> and <filename>libtool</filename> versions
<emphasis>on your development system</emphasis>, so please make sure they
are current releases before creating a tarball for public
consumption.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Run <command>make distcheck</command>. If your system
requires any special parameters to be given to configure for it to complete
(like <command>--with-libxml2</command>, for example), then you can use
<command>make DISTCHECK_CONFIGURE_FLAGS=&quot;...&quot; distcheck</command>
to supply those parameters. The distcheck process will actually unpack the
tarball into a temporary directory, and run a complete
configure/make/install/uninstall process on it to ensure that no build
errors occur. This step should be considered to be mandatory before
releasing your tarball to the general public.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>
