<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="chapter-general" xreflabel="Chapter 2">
<?dbhtml dir="chapter02"?>
<title>Overall Description</title>
<?dbhtml filename="chapter02.html"?>

<section id="ch-gen-functions">
<title>alfs Functions</title>

<para>alfs is designed to be the most complete implementation of the ALFS schema
syntax specification.  It is designed to support complete automation in the
creation (build) of Linux From Scratch systems.  The ALFS schema is an XML
specification that handles the outline of a procedure to be processed by the
application.  This outline is referred to as a profile.  Each profile can be a
small set of commands for basic tasks or a large set of commands to build an
entire system including all LFS and BLFS packages.  When alfs reads a profile,
it parses the XML into internal command structures and uses its own library of
internal shared objects to perform the actual work.  alfs will not
&quot;reinvent the wheel&quot; so to speak with regards to basic system commands
like <command>make</command>, or <command>cp</command>.  The shared objects are
wrappers and translators for alfs to use to take the XML profile and run system
commands.</para>

<para>alfs will also support an extensive logging XML schema.  This new schema
is designed to provide a large amount of logging facilities that current Linux
systems support, but not in one place or within one tool.  Most Linux users must
use Bash shell scripts or other wrapper type scripts to pull these tools
together to perform debugging, troubleshooting or comparative analysis of a
build.</para>
</section>

<section id="ch-gen-similarsys">
<title>Similar Systems</title>
<para>alfs is the natural successor to nALFS. It will provide backwards
compatibility but with extended, optional, functionality.  alfs can be used as a
direct replacement for nALFS. It should be noted here that alfs will be a
complete rewrite of nALFS.</para>
</section>

<section id="ch-gen-impl">
<title>alfs Implementation Highlights</title>

<para>alfs will support the following concepts:</para>
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem><para>Complete separation of a backend server daemon which carries
    out the specific tasks and a frontend client that initiates the
    instructions.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><para>Validation of profiles before any other actions take place.
  </para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>Downloading and checking of packages from both local and
  external locations.</para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>Dependency resolution to ensure a package never gets installed
  unless it has its dependencies satisfied.</para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>A comprehensive and informational logging system.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><para>A package uninstallation feature.</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>Allow support for different clients.</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>Ability to handle conditional executions.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</section>
</chapter>
