<chapter id="intro-welcome" xreflabel="Welcome">
<?dbhtml filename="welcome/welcome.html" dir="introduction"?>
<title>Welcome to the &book-product; Users Guide</title>

<sect1>

<para>LFS stands for Linux From Scratch and it's a project, led by 

<ulink url="mailto:gerard@linuxfromscratch.org">Gerard Beekmans</ulink> 

&emdash;&lt;gerard@linuxfromscratch.org&gt;, which helps you build your own 
Linux system.</para>

<para>What this means is that you will use nothing but the source code of
various software packages needed for a fully functional Linux system. You
will compile the packages one-by-one on your own computer. During this
process, you will be able to tweak every single corner of your system, by
editing a bunch of configuration files, creating your own boot scripts
etc.</para>

<para>All this might sound a bit complicated and require too much work. But
even if it is, it's well worth it. One of the LFS project's secondary goals
is education. Great care is taken in each step to explain what is occuring
at each phase of the build procedure.</para>

<para>Best of all it that it does not have to be that complicated or time
consuming. With only a few keystrokes and the right software, you can just
sit back and relax, while your system is being built &emdash; from scratch.
This is where the ALFS project comes into play.</para>

<para>ALFS stands for Automated Linux From Scratch, and its aim is to
provide a much simpler method for building a Linux system.</para>

<para>ALFS uses profiles (simple XML files) which describe what actions are
to be taken and what commands executed.  Feeding the program (like
&book-product;) with those profiles, will make the program act upon
them.</para>

<para>For example, if you want to create a directory, all you have to do is
to put:</para>

<screen><command>&lt;mkdir&gt;
	&lt;name&gt;/some/directory&lt;/name&gt;
&lt;/mkdir&gt;</command></screen>

<para>in the profile and leave the rest to the program. Of course, you are
not limited to just compiling packages for LFS. You can do just about
anything. All it takes is a little time to write a profile for it.</para>

<para>This might seem very similar to ordinary shell scripting, but it has
also a lot of advantages. With this approach &book-product; (after reading
any properly formatted profile) can be instructed to pause execution, start
execution from a selected element (by browsing a profile in a tree-like
mode), enter special environments like <filename>chroot</filename>, and
much much more.</para>

</sect1>

&intro-welcome-acknowledgements;
&intro-welcome-conventions;
&intro-welcome-contactinfo;
&intro-welcome-changelog;

</chapter>
