<!--
        $LastChangedDate$
        $LastChangedBy$
        $LastChangedRevision$ 
-->

<sect1 id="hacker-coding-style" xreflabel="Coding Style">
<?dbhtml filename="coding-style.html" dir="hacker"?>
<title>Coding Style</title>

<para>The development team would like to keep a clean and standardized coding
style in the product's code. This will make it easier for everyone to read the
code.</para>

<para>Linux's creator Linus Torvalds has provided an excellent coding style
for us to use. He even gives it to us in the Linux Kernel source distribution
tarball. We have provided the version from Linux v2.4.22 in its entirety for
your reference (and to comply with the GDL).</para>

<para>It should be noted, however, that not all of the coding style written by
Linus is applicable to &book-product;. The sections (a.k.a chapters) that can
be ignored are:</para>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Chapter 7: Configuration-files</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Chapter 8: Data structures</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

<para><filename>--------------------------------------------------
</filename></para>

<sect2>
<title>Linux Kernel Coding Style</title>

<para>This is a short document describing the preferred coding style for
the linux kernel. Coding style is very personal, and I won't
<emphasis role="bold">force</emphasis> my views on anybody, but this is
what goes for anything that I have to be able to maintain, and I'd prefer
it for most other things too. Please at least consider the points made
here.</para>

<para>First off, I'd suggest printing out a copy of the GNU coding
standards, and <emphasis role="bold">NOT</emphasis> read it.  Burn them,
it's a great symbolic gesture.</para>

<para>Anyway, here goes:</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Chapter 1: Indentation</title>

<para>Tabs are 8 characters, and thus indentations are also 8 characters.
There are heretic movements that try to make indentations 4 (or even 2!)
characters deep, and that is akin to trying to define the value of PI to be
3.</para>

<para>Rationale: The whole idea behind indentation is to clearly define
where a block of control starts and ends. Especially when you've been
looking at your screen for 20 straight hours, you'll find it a lot easier
to see how the indentation works if you have large indentations.</para>

<para>Now, some people will claim that having 8-character indentations
makes the code move too far to the right, and makes it hard to read on a
80-character terminal screen. The answer to that is that if you need more
than 3 levels of indentation, you're screwed anyway, and should fix your
program.</para>

<para>In short, 8-char indents make things easier to read, and have the added
benefit of warning you when you're nesting your functions too deep. Heed that
warning.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Chapter 2: Placing Braces</title>

<para>The other issue that always comes up in C styling is the placement of
braces. Unlike the indent size, there are few technical reasons to choose one
placement strategy over the other, but the preferred way, as shown to us by
the prophets Kernighan and Ritchie, is to put the opening brace last on the
line, and put the closing brace first, thusly:</para>

<screen><command>if (x is true) {
	we do y
}</command></screen>

<para>However, there is one special case, namely functions: they have the
opening brace at the beginning of the next line, thus:</para>

<screen><command>int function(int x)
{
	body of function
}</command></screen>

<para>Heretic people all over the world have claimed that this
inconsistency is ... well ...  inconsistent, but all right-thinking people
know that (a) K&amp;R are <emphasis role="bold">right</emphasis> and (b)
K&amp;R are <emphasis role="bold">right</emphasis>. Besides, functions are
special anyway (you can't nest them in C).</para>

<para>Note that the closing brace is empty on a line of its own,
<emphasis role="bold">except</emphasis> in the cases where it is followed
by a continuation of the same statement, ie a <filename>while</filename> in
a do-statement or an <filename>else</filename> in an if-statement, like
this:</para>

<screen><command>do {
	body of do-loop
} while (condition);</command></screen>

<para>and</para>

<screen><command>if (x == y) {
	..
} else if (x > y) {
	...
} else {
	....
}</command></screen>

<para>Rationale: K&amp;R.</para>

<para>Also, note that this brace-placement also minimizes the number of
empty (or almost empty) lines, without any loss of readability. Thus, as
the supply of new-lines on your screen is not a renewable resource (think
25-line terminal screens here), you have more empty lines to put comments
on.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Chapter 3: Naming</title>

<para>C is a Spartan language, and so should your naming be. Unlike
Modula-2 and Pascal programmers, C programmers do not use cute names like
ThisVariableIsATemporaryCounter. A C programmer would call that variable
<filename>tmp</filename>, which is much easier to write, and not the least
more difficult to understand.</para>

<para><emphasis role="bold">HOWEVER</emphasis>, while mixed-case names are
frowned upon, descriptive names for global variables are a must. To call a
global function <filename>foo</filename> is a shooting offense.</para>

<para><emphasis role="bold">GLOBAL</emphasis> variables (to be used only if
you <emphasis role="bold">really</emphasis> need them) need to have
descriptive names, as do global functions. If you have a function that
counts the number of active users, you should call that
<filename>count_active_users()</filename> or similar, you should <emphasis
role="bold">not</emphasis> call it <filename>cntusr()</filename>.</para>

<para>Encoding the type of a function into the name (so-called Hungarian
notation) is brain damaged &emdash; the compiler knows the types anyway and
can check those, and it only confuses the programmer. No wonder MicroSoft
makes buggy programs.</para>

<para><emphasis role="bold">LOCAL</emphasis> variable names should be
short, and to the point. If you have some random integer loop counter, it
should probably be called <filename>i</filename>. Calling it
<filename>loop_counter</filename> is non-productive, if there is no chance
of it being mis-understood.  Similarly, <filename>tmp</filename> can be
just about any type of variable that is used to hold a temporary
value.</para>

<para>If you are afraid to mix up your local variable names, you have another
problem, which is called the function-growth-hormone-imbalance syndrome. See
next chapter.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Chapter 4: Functions</title>

<para>Functions should be short and sweet, and do just one thing. They should
fit on one or two screenfuls of text (the ISO/ANSI screen size is 80x24, as we
all know), and do one thing and do that well.</para>

<para>The maximum length of a function is inversely proportional to the
complexity and indentation level of that function. So, if you have a
conceptually simple function that is just one long (but simple) case-
statement, where you have to do lots of small things for a lot of different
cases, it's OK to have a longer function.</para>

<para>However, if you have a complex function, and you suspect that a less-
than-gifted first-year high-school student might not even understand what the
function is all about, you should adhere to the maximum limits all the more
closely. Use helper functions with descriptive names (you can ask the
compiler to in-line them if you think it's performance-critical, and it will
probably do a better job of it that you would have done).</para>

<para>Another measure of the function is the number of local variables. They
shouldn't exceed 5-10, or you're doing something wrong. Re-think the
function, and split it into smaller pieces. A human brain can generally
easily keep track of about 7 different things, anything more and it gets
confused. You know you're brilliant, but maybe you'd like to understand what
you did 2 weeks from now.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Chapter 5: Commenting</title>

<para>Comments are good, but there is also a danger of over-commenting.
<emphasis role="bold">NEVER</emphasis> try to explain <emphasis
role="bold">HOW</emphasis> your code works in a comment: it's much better
to write the code so that the <emphasis role="bold">working</emphasis> is
obvious, and it's a waste of time to explain badly written code.</para>

<para>Generally, you want your comments to tell <emphasis
role="bold">WHAT</emphasis> your code does, not <emphasis
role="bold">HOW</emphasis>. Also, try to avoid putting comments inside a
function body: if the function is so complex that you need to separately
comment parts of it, you should probably go back to chapter 4 for a while.
You can make small comments to note or warn about something particularly
clever (or ugly), but try to avoid excess. Instead, put the comments at the
head of the function, telling people what it does, and possibly <emphasis
role="bold">WHY</emphasis> it does it.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Chapter 6: You've made a mess of it</title>

<para>That's OK, we all do. You've probably been told by your long-time
Unix user helper that GNU <filename>emacs</filename> automatically formats
the C sources for you, and you've noticed that yes, it does do that, but
the defaults it uses are less than desirable (in fact, they are worse than
random typing &emdash; a infinite number of monkeys typing into GNU
<filename>emacs</filename> would never make a good program).</para>

<para>So, you can either get rid of GNU <filename>emacs</filename>, or
change it to use saner values.  To do the latter, you can stick the
following in your <filename>.emacs</filename> file:</para>

<screen><command>(defun linux-c-mode ()
  &quot;C mode with adjusted defaults for use with the Linux kernel.&quot;
  (interactive)
  (c-mode)
  (c-set-style &quot;K&amp;R&quot;)
  (setq c-basic-offset 8))</command></screen>

<para>This will define the <filename>M-x linux-c-mode</filename> command. When
hacking on a module, if you put the string <filename>-*- linux-c -*-
</filename> somewhere on the first two lines, this mode will be automatically
invoked. Also, you may want to add</para>

<screen><command>(setq auto-mode-alist (cons '(&quot;/usr/src/linux.*/.*\\.[ch]$&quot; . linux-c-mode)
      auto-mode-alist))</command></screen>

<para>to your <filename>.emacs</filename> file if you want to have
<filename>linux-c-</filename> mode switched on automagically when you edit
source files under <filename>/usr/src/linux</filename>.</para>

<para>But even if you fail in getting emacs to do sane formatting, not
everything is lost: use <filename>indent</filename>.</para>

<para>Now, again, GNU <filename>indent</filename> has the same brain dead
settings that GNU <filename>emacs</filename> has, which is why you need to
give it a few command line options. However, that's not too bad, because
even the makers of GNU <filename>indent</filename> recognize the authority
of K&amp;R (the GNU people aren't evil, they are just severely misguided in
this matter), so you just give indent the options <filename>-kr -
i8</filename> (stands for &quot;K&amp;R, 8 character indents&quot;).</para>

<para><filename>indent</filename> has a lot of options, and especially when
it comes to comment re-formatting you may want to take a look at the manual
page.  But remember: <filename>indent</filename> is not a fix for bad
programming.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Chapter 7: Configuration-files</title>

<para>For configuration options (<filename>arch/xxx/config.in</filename>,
and all the <filename>Config.in</filename> files), somewhat different
indentation is used.</para>

<para>An indention level of 3 is used in the code, while the text in the
config- options should have an indention-level of 2 to indicate
dependencies. The latter only applies to bool/tristate options. For other
options, just use common sense. An example:</para>

<screen><command>if [ &quot;$CONFIG_EXPERIMENTAL&quot; = &quot;y&quot; ]; then
   tristate 'Apply nitroglycerine inside the keyboard (DANGEROUS)' CONFIG_BOOM
   if [ &quot;$CONFIG_BOOM&quot; != &quot;n&quot; ]; then
      bool '  Output nice messages when you explode' CONFIG_CHEER
   fi
fi</command></screen>

<para>Generally, CONFIG_EXPERIMENTAL should surround all options not
considered stable. All options that are known to trash data (experimental
write- support for file-systems, for instance) should be denoted
(DANGEROUS), other Experimental options should be denoted
(EXPERIMENTAL).</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Chapter 8: Data structures</title>

<para>Data structures that have visibility outside the single-threaded
environment they are created and destroyed in should always have reference
counts. In the kernel, garbage collection doesn't exist (and outside the
kernel garbage collection is slow and inefficient), which means that you
absolutely <emphasis role="bold">have</emphasis> to reference count all
your uses.</para>

<para>Reference counting means that you can avoid locking, and allows
multiple users to have access to the data structure in parallel &emdash;
and not having to worry about the structure suddenly going away from under
them just because they slept or did something else for a while.</para>

<para>Note that locking is <emphasis role="bold">not</emphasis> a
replacement for reference counting. Locking is used to keep data structures
coherent, while reference counting is a memory management technique.
Usually both are needed, and they are not to be confused with each
other.</para>

<para>Many data structures can indeed have two levels of reference
counting, when there are users of different &quot;classes&quot;. The
subclass count counts the number of subclass users, and decrements the
global count just once when the subclass count goes to zero.</para>

<para>Examples of this kind of &quot;multi-reference-counting&quot; can be
found in memory management (<filename>struct mm_struct</filename>:
<filename>mm_users</filename> and <filename>mm_count</filename>), and in
filesystem code (<filename>struct super_block</filename>:
<filename>s_count</filename> and <filename>s_active</filename>).</para>

<para>Remember: if another thread can find your data structure, and you
don't have a reference count on it, you almost certainly have a bug.</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>
