<!--
        $LastChangedDate$
        $LastChangedBy$
        $LastChangedRevision$ 
-->

<sect1 id="hacker-distro-tarballs" xreflabel="Distribution Tarballs">
<?dbhtml filename="distro_tarballs.html" dir="hacker"?>
<title>Distribution Tarballs</title>

<para>When you are ready to produce a tarball for distribution, there are a
few steps to follow:</para>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Check out a clean copy of nALFS from the SVN repository.
Using an existing copy, especially one that has been configured and used
as a build tree, can potentially cause errors in the <command>make
dist</command> process.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Edit <filename>bootstrap.configure</filename>, and
modify the line starting with AC_INIT to reflect the version number that
you want the distribution to be given (replace &quot;SVN&quot; with your
desired version number). Do not commit this change to the SVN
repository, as the SVN version should always report its version number
as &quot;SVN&quot;.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Run <command>aclocal</command> to ensure that your
<filename>aclocal.m4</filename> file is up to date.</para></listitem>

<listitem>

<para>Run <command>sh ./bootstrap</command> with some parameters (to be
explained).  This command will create the configure script and Makefile
(as is normally done with a SVN checkout), but will also download,
extract and rename the documentation files that will be included in the
tarball. These files include the DTD, the syntax document describing the
DTD, the user's guide and the hacker's guide. The latter three documents
are currently downloaded from the ALFS/downloads ares on the LFS server.
See the URL_BASE variable in the bootstrap script to change the download
source.</para>

<para>The <command>bootstrap</command> shell script supports multiple
parameters.  The <command>-d</command> parameter will download the
version of the nALFS DTD specified.  To get the SVN trunk use
<command>-d trunk</command>.  The <command>-s</command> parameter will
download the version of the ALFS DTD Syntax Doc specified.  To get the
SVN trunk use <command>-s SVN</command>.  To get a named version (e.g.
v3.1) use <command>-s 3.1</command>.  The <command>-u</command> and
<command>-h</command> parameters will download the version of the nALFS
User's Guide and Hacker's Guide respectively.  They work just like the
<command>-s</command> parameter does.  The <command>-p</command> will
download the version of the official LFS stable profile specified.  It
works like the <command>-d</command> parameter.</para>

<para>A good example for reference: <command>sh ./bootstrap -d trunk -s
SVN -u SVN -h SVN -p 5.1.1-5</command></para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

<note><para>If you want to add more than one profile version to the
distribution tarball, you can rerun <command>bootstrap</command> many
times with just the <command>-p</command> parameter.</para></note>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Run <command>./configure</command> specifying any
parameters your system needs to complete the configuration
process.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Run <command>make dist</command>. This will produce both
a <filename>.tar.gz</filename> and a <filename>.tar.bz2</filename> file
in the current directory containing everything that should be needed to
build &book-product; on an end-user's system. Note that this tarball
will be created using the <filename>autoconf</filename>,
<filename>automake</filename> and <filename>libtool</filename> versions
<emphasis>on your development system</emphasis>, so please make sure
they are current releases before creating a tarball for public
consumption.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Run <command>make distcheck</command>. If your system
requires any special parameters to be given to configure for it to
complete (like <command>--with-libxml2</command>, for example), then you
can use <command>make DISTCHECK_CONFIGURE_FLAGS=&quot;...&quot;
distcheck</command> to supply those parameters.  The distcheck process
will actually unpack the tarball into a temporary directory, and run a
complete configure/make/install/uninstall process on it to ensure that
no build errors occur. This step should be considered to be mandatory
before releasing your tarball to the general public.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>
