<!--
        $LastChangedDate$
        $LastChangedBy$
        $LastChangedRevision$ 
-->

<sect1 id="hacker-svn" xreflabel="&book-product; Code from SVN">
<?dbhtml filename="svn.html" dir="hacker"?>
<title>Code from SVN</title>

<sect2>
<title>Usage</title>

<para>Before you can follow these instructions, you will need to have
acquired a copy of the &book-product; source code from the SVN
repository.  You can get that from <xref linkend="common-svn"/>.</para>

<para>The repository copy of the &book-product; source code does not
include an executable <filename>configure</filename> script nor a
<filename>Makefile</filename>. This is by design, as there is a script
to create them, which ensures that their contents will always be up to
date with the source tree contents and not require manual
editing.</para>

<para>&book-product; has been configured to use the GNU
<filename>autotools</filename> suite for its build process. The build
system was created using <filename>autoconf-2.57</filename>,
<filename>automake-1.7.7</filename> and
<filename>libtool-1.5</filename>.  If you use older versions than those,
you may experience warnings and/or outright failures
(<filename>automake-1.6</filename> is known to be unable to handle the
&book-product; <filename>Makefile.am</filename>) file.</para>

<para>After you checkout the &book-product; source tree, you will need
to execute&nbsp;:</para>

<screen><command>sh ./bootstrap</command></screen>

<para>in the &book-product; root directory itself. This should result
output similar to the following:</para>

<screen><command>$ sh ./bootstrap</command>
You should update your 'aclocal.m4' by running aclocal.
Putting files in AC_CONFIG_AUX_DIR, `gnubuild'.
configure.ac: installing 'gnubuild/install-sh'
configure.ac: installing 'gnubuild/mkinstalldirs'
configure.ac: installing 'gnubuild/missing'
Makefile.am: installing 'gnubuild/compile'
Makefile.am: installing 'gnubuild/depcomp'
patching file ltmain.sh
Hunk #1 succeeded at 160 with fuzz 2 (offset -78 lines).
Hunk #2 succeeded at 269 with fuzz 1.
Hunk #3 succeeded at 4483 (offset -1172 lines).</screen>

<para>This output comes from the <filename>autoreconf</filename> tool,
which is part of the <filename>autoconf</filename> package, that
automatically runs <filename>libtoolize</filename>,
<filename>autoheader</filename>, <filename>aclocal</filename> and other
parts of the <filename>autotools</filename> suite. The warning about
&quot;update your 'aclocal.m4'&quot; can be ignored, as
<filename>aclocal</filename> is already executed later by
<filename>autoreconf</filename>. The <filename>patch</filename> offset
and/or fuzz messages about <filename>ltmain.sh</filename> are caused by
the <filename>bootstrap</filename> script applying a patch created
against <filename>libtool-1.5</filename>; if your
<filename>libtool</filename> version is different, the patch should
still work correctly, but you may see messages like this from the
<filename>patch</filename> command. In the worst case, the patch fails
to apply, the &book-product; build will still be functional, but
<filename>libtool</filename> will generate more output messages than
necessary.</para>

<para>Once <filename>bootstrap</filename> has been run, you can execute
<filename>./configure</filename> like any other GNU autoconf-based package
to configure &book-product; for your system.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Editing source files</title>

<para>The &book-product; build system, because it uses
<filename>automake</filename>, has full dependency tracking on all files
used to build the binaries. This will reduce your rebuilding time as you
edit header files and source files, as the make system will know exactly
what must be rebuilt.</para>

<para>In addition, if you are going to make changes to
<filename>bootstrap</filename>, you should add the
<filename>&quot;--enable-maintainer-mode&quot;</filename> parameter to
your <filename>configure</filename> command. With this done, each time
you edit and re-run <filename>bootstrap</filename>, the
<filename>Makefile</filename> will automatically re-run
<filename>configure</filename> to make your changes take effect. Be
warned though, that if you manually edit
<filename>Makefile.am</filename> or <filename>configure.ac</filename>,
you must modify the <filename>bootstrap</filename> script to incorporate
your changes, because these files are not stored in the CVS
repository.</para>

<para>If you add any C source files to the tree, you will need to rerun
the <filename>bootstrap</filename> script to get them included in your
build.  If you add header files, it is not necessary to rerun the
<filename>bootstrap</filename> script unless you plan on using &quot;make
dist&quot; from that same tree, in which case those added headers would not
get included into the tarball.</para>

<para>If you add or remove &quot;syntax versions&quot; in any of the
handlers, you must re-run <filename>bootstrap</filename> to get the version
lists in <filename>Makefile.am</filename> and
<filename>configure.ac</filename> to incorporate your changes, or you will
experience unusual build behavior.</para>

<para>If you add or remove any program options in
<filename>src/options.h</filename>, you must re-run
<filename>bootstrap</filename> to regenerate
<filename>src/option-list.h</filename>.  Without that file being
regenerated, you may experience compile errors or find that your newly
added option does not work properly.</para>

<para>All other types of files fall into two categories:</para>

<blockquote><para>those that should be present 
<emphasis role="bold">only</emphasis> in the SVN repository</para>
</blockquote>

<para>Nothing needs to be done for these files, other than the relevant
&quot;cvs add&quot; commands.</para>

<blockquote><para>those that should be added to the distribution
tarball</para></blockquote>

<para>The <filename>bootstrap.Makefile</filename> script will need to be
edited, specifically the line that sets <filename>EXTRA_DIST</filename>
near the beginning of the script. Add the path(s) to the new files to this
line, or add an additional line starting with &quot;<filename>EXTRA_DIST
+=</filename>&quot; (standard GNU makefile syntax). If the files are not
listed on this line, they will not be included in the tarball created by
<command>make dist</command>.</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>
