<sect2 id="ch0-introduction" xreflabel="Introduction">
<?dbhtml filename="introduction.html" dir="chapter00"?>
<title>Introduction</title>

<para><acronym>LFS</acronym> stands for Linux From Scratch and it's a project, 
led by <ulink url="mailto:gerard@linuxfromscratch.org">Gerard 
Beekmans</ulink>&nbsp;&nbsp;&lt;gerard@linuxfromscratch.org&gt;, which helps 
you build your own Linux system.</para>

<para>What this means is that you will use nothing but the source code of 
various software packages needed for a fully functional Linux system. You will 
compile the packages one-by-one on your own computer. During this process, you 
will be able to tweak every single corner of your system, by editing a bunch of 
configuration files, creating your own boot scripts etc.</para>

<para>All this might sound a bit complicated and require too much work. But 
even if it is, it's well worth it. One of the <acronym>LFS</acronym> project's 
secondary goals is education. Great care is taken in each step to explain what 
is occuring at each phase of the build procedure.</para>

<para>Best of all it that it does not have to be that complicated or time 
consuming. With only a few keystrokes and the right software, you can just sit 
back and relax, while your system is being built &emdash; from scratch. This 
is where the <acronym>ALFS</acronym> project comes into play.</para>

<para><acronym>ALFS</acronym> stands for Automated Linux From Scratch, and its 
aim is to provide a much simpler method for building a Linux system.</para>

<para><acronym>ALFS</acronym> uses profiles (simple <acronym>XML</acronym> 
files) which describe what actions are to be taken and what commands executed. 
Feeding the program (like &book-product;) with those profiles, will make the 
program act upon them.</para>

<para>For example, if you want to create a directory, all you have to do is
to put:</para>

<screen><command>&lt;mkdir&gt;
	&lt;name&gt;/some/directory&lt;/name&gt;
&lt;/mkdir&gt;</command></screen>

<para>in the profile and leave the rest to the program. Of course, you are not 
limited to just compiling packages for <acronym>LFS</acronym>. You can do just 
about anything.</para>

<para>This might seem very similar to ordinary shell scripting, but it has 
also a lot of advantages. With this approach &book-product;, after reading any 
properly formatted profile, can be instructed to pause execution, start 
execution from selected element (by browsing a profile in a tree-like mode) 
and much much more.</para>

</sect2>

