<!--
        $LastChangedDate$
        $LastChangedBy$
        $LastChangedRevision$ 
-->

<chapter id="editor-editor" xreflabel="Editor">
<?dbhtml filename="editor/editor.html" dir="part3"?>
<title>Common Elements for all &book-product; Documentation Editors</title>

<sect1>

<para>Editing the guides for &book-product; is not difficult at any
stretch of the imagination. The biggest piece is have an understanding of
the DocBook XML DTD. The DTD's <ulink url="http://docbook.org/">home
page</ulink> has a lot of information on how to use it and <ulink
url="http://docbook.org/tdg/en/html/docbook.html">a book</ulink> is also
available.</para>

<para>The &book-product; books (or guides) each have their own unique
design and layout.  They all, however, share some common pieces.</para>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>As mentioned above, they are all written using the
DocBook XML DTD v4.3.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>They all can be parsed into
three formats: chunks-html, nochunks-html and
flat-text.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Each has a Preface that contains: a foreward, the
guide's organization, a &quot;Who would want to read this&quot; section
and finally a prerequisites page.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Each has an Introduction that contains: a welcome page,
acknowledgements, document conventions, contact info and changelog.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

<para>This is where the similarities end.  After this point, each book
takes on the characteristics necessary for its audience.</para>

<para>The books are available from the SVN repository.  See the <xref
linkend="common-svn"/> page for instructions.  In the root of the
guide's source tree is a <filename>README</filename> file.  It provides
the necessary instructions to help you install the tools that you will
need to use the makefile to parse the XML source into one of the three
rendered editions.</para>

<para><emphasis role="bold">A note on version numbers</emphasis>&nbsp;:
The guides each have a separate version number.  The number is split
into two pieces.  The first piece is the major and minor version of
&book-product; that the guide is written for.  The second piece is the
version of the guide itself.  The version numbering scheme is set up
this way to ensure that a reader will know that the version of the guide
they are reading goes with the version of the package they are using.
The version number of the ALFS DTD syntax document is special.  It is
versioned to be the same as the version of the DTD itself.  The ALFS DTD
is special in this regard.  &book-product; uses the DTD, but the DTD is
&quot;implementation agnostic&quot; and keeps its own version number
separate from any implementation (&book-product; is one implementation
of the ALFS DTD).</para>

</sect1>

</chapter>

