<sect1 id="common-bugzilla" xreflabel="Bugzilla">
<?dbhtml filename="bugzilla.html" dir="common"?>
<title>Bugzilla</title>

<para>The &book-product; package tracks all &quot;<emphasis
role="bold">bugs</emphasis>&quot; in the LFS Bugzilla database. A
&quot;<emphasis role="bold">bug</emphasis>&quot; is defined as an issue,
todo or enhancement request tied to one of the ALFS products. The Bugzilla
database can be accessed via the web at&nbsp;<ulink
url="&bugzilla-root;">&bugzilla-root;</ulink>. The package is split across
two Bugzilla products: &quot;<emphasis role="bold">ALFS
Profiles</emphasis>&quot; and &quot;<emphasis role="bold">Automated Linux
From Scratch</emphasis>&quot;. The distinction between the two should be
pretty clear.</para>

<para>The &quot;<emphasis role="bold">Automated Linux From
Scratch</emphasis>&quot; product is then split up into five components:
&quot;<emphasis role="bold">Back End (XML)</emphasis>&quot;,
&quot;<emphasis role="bold">Doc</emphasis>s&quot;, &quot;<emphasis
role="bold">DTD</emphasis>&quot;, &quot;<emphasis
role="bold">Extras</emphasis>&quot;, and &quot;<emphasis role="bold">Front
End (GUI)</emphasis>&quot;. The &quot;<emphasis role="bold">Back End
(XML)</emphasis>&quot; component is for all of the back end handlers that
parse the XML and perform the work they ask for. The &quot;<emphasis
role="bold">Docs</emphasis>&quot; component is to track all issues related
to the three works (this book, the ALFS DTD Syntax Doc and the Users
Guide). The &quot;<emphasis role="bold">DTD</emphasis>&quot; component is
designed to take care of all issues around the main ALFS DTD and any other
DTD's that the project uses. A good example would be the logging DTD.  The
&quot;<emphasis role="bold">Extras</emphasis>&quot; component is for any
add-ons or extras to the &book-product; package. The &quot;<emphasis
role="bold">Front End (GUI)</emphasis>&quot; is designed to track any bugs
for the <filename>ncurses</filename> GUI.</para>

<para>If you find a bug in one of the products, first look in the Bugzilla
database to see if you issue is there.  If not, then please read the <xref
linkend="intro-welcome-contactinfo"/> page on how to contact the
development team at the appropriate list. The team will decide if your
issue is really a bug or just user error. If a bug is found, then you can
or one of the development team will add the bug in the database for work on
later.</para>

</sect1>
